Guide to the Clifford K. Berryman cartoon collection, 1899-1949 MS2024
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Clifford K. Berryman cartoon collection
1899-1949
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Berryman, Clifford Kennedy
MS2024
13 Linear Feet
Collection consist of cartoons (209), Christmas cards (12), and facsimiles of cartoons (3), all drawn by Clifford K. Berryman. The cartoons with identified dates span the years 1899-1949, thus exemplifying Berryman's work over much of his career. Berryman was employed as a cartoonist by the Washington Post from 1891-1970 and by the Washington Star from 1907-49. There are only a handful of cartoons which were composed before 1907, when Berryman left the Washington Post to draw for the Washington Star. Conversely, a substantial portion of the cartoons (at least 50) date from the last 3 years (1946-1949) of Berryman's long career. About 135 of the items have been date-identified while the remainder are undated.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
In 1977, Berryman's daughter, Florence Seville Berryman, donated this collection of Berryman cartoons to The George Washington University. 1983, Ms. Berryman also donated Gridiron Nights and Report from Tokyo (illustrated by Berryman), and other art books.
Historical or Biographical Note
In April 1949, around his eightieth birthday, Clifford K. Berryman received a letter from then-President Harry S. Truman. Though Berryman had been vice president of the Association of Oldest Inhabitants of the District, Truman found Berryman to be truly "ageless and timeless." In an often-quoted passage, Truman went further to write that "Presidents, Senators, and even Supreme Court Justices come and go but the [Washington] Monument and Berryman stand." Only seven months later, the "Dean of American Cartoonists" collapsed in the lobby of the Washington Star, on his way to work. On December 11, 1949 he passed away at home, at 2114 Bancroft Place, NW, of a heart ailment. He was buried in Glenwood Cemetery.
Clifford Kennedy Berryman was born in Kentucky on April 2, 1869, one of James Thomas and Sallie (Church) Berryman's eleven children. James Berryman was a commission merchant, farmer, and/or grain dealer who entertained family members and neighbors with sketches of "hillbillies" in their hometown. Clifford inherited his father's talent, and after he graduated from Prof. Henry's School for Boys in Versailles, KY, he was appointed as a draftsman to the United States Patent Office in Washington, D.C. From 1886 to 1891, Berryman delineated patent entries for $30 per month. He began to submit cartoons to the Washington Post, and in 1891 he became an understudy to the Post's cartoonist, George Y. Coffin (some of whose cartoons are also at Gelman Library). When Coffin died in 1896, Berryman replaced him. Berryman stayed with the Post until 1907, when he was hired by the Washington Star, which had a larger circulation at the time. Clifford Berryman drew political cartoons for the Star for the next 42 years, up until his death.
Commenting on Clifford K. Berryman's work, politicians, artists, and reference books note that Berryman cartoons lack the maliciousness that has been a part of American politics throughout the twentieth century. Himself a Democrat, Berryman satirized political figures from both the Democratic party and the G.O.P.. Though he is best known for the November 16, 1902 Washington Post cartoon "Drawing The Line In Mississippi" which portrayed a "teddy bear" for the first time, Berryman's copious work has earned recognition in many venues. In 1944, he won the Pulitzer Prize for editorial cartooning for "But Where Is The Boat Going?", which showed then-president Franklin D. Roosevelt and various government officials trying to steer, in opposite directions, the "USS Manpower Mobilization". The magazine Journalism & Mass Communication Educator, in its Spring 1998 issue, listed Clifford Berryman (along with Thomas Nast and Pat Oliphant) as some of ten cartoonists who have made an "outstanding contribution to American journalism".
In July 1893, Berryman married Kate Geddes, the daughter of engraver George Washington Durfee. The couple had three children: Mary Belle, who died as an infant; Florence Seville (an art critic), and John Thomas (also a Pulitzer-Prize winning cartoonist). Alongside his work at the drawing board, Berryman was an active member of the Washington Heights Presbyterian Church at 1862 Kalorama Road. He was also the first cartoonist to become a member of the Gridiron Club, and was its president in 1926.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection consist of cartoons (209), Christmas cards (12), and facsimiles of cartoons (3), all drawn by Clifford K. Berryman. The cartoons with identified dates span the years 1899-1949, thus exemplifying Berryman's work over much of his career. Berryman was employed as a cartoonist by the Washington Post from 1891-1907 and by the Washington Star from 1907-49. There are only a handful of cartoons which were composed before 1907, when Berryman left the Washington Post to draw for the Washington Star. Conversely, a substantial portion of the cartoons (at least 50) date from the last 3 years (1946-1949) of Berryman's long career. About 135 of the items have been date-identified while the remainder are undated.
In large part, Berryman's subjects are American Presidents and political figures, as well as political events and controversies of national import. There are a number of cartoons depicting former Presidents Theodore Roosevelt, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Harry S. Truman, as well as presidential candidates like Alfred E. Smith. Congressmen and state government leaders also make frequent appearances in Berryman's work. The cartoons broach nationally debated problems and interests such as: drought, farm relief, and food prices; representation of the District of Columbia in Congress; labor strikes and legislation; campaigning and elections; political patronage; European coronations; the America's Cup; and the Atomic Bomb.
Florence Berryman was an alumnae of The George Washington University (class of 1924), and her father received an honorary MA from the University.
Berryman drew thousands of cartoons, often giving them away to libraries and political figures who requested or exhibited them. Substantial collections can therefore be found in a number of cultural institutions in Washington D.C., where Berryman lived and worked for more than 50 years including the Library of Congress and National Archives. American chief executives from Grover Cleveland to Harry Truman were known to collect Berryman's work, so archives documenting the presidency are also likely to own some Berryman cartoons.
Collection note
Other than the Christmas cards, nearly all of the Berryman cartoons range in size from 13 x 15" to 16" x 20" and except for the Christmas cards and cartoon facsimiles
Related Materials
The following collection contains a George Washington University bookplate designed by Clifford Berryman, University Historical Materials RG0031 Series 13 Oversize Box 1.
United States. Congress; Cartoonists; Presidents; Political satire; Washington (D.C.); Berryman, Clifford Kennedy
- "Anti-Progress", 1899 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General note
  Shows a man riding a donkey and carrying a flag labeled "Democracy" running on a treadmill labeled "Aguinaldo Platform"
- "Labor Day 1901", 1901 September 02 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  shows a factory with sign "Closed Today Only" and female figure leading the working man away
- "John Bull's Real Work Is Just Beginning", 1902 June 05 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  shows figure representing England leading an orchestra in playing "God Save The King"
- No title, 1931 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows Ebenezer Scrooge and a young boy
- No title, 1932 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows George Washington (?) approaching a house
- No title, 1933 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows 17th century family enjoying Christmas dinner. Man in card is reported to be Samuel Pepys.
- No title, 1934 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows Santa Claus as a pied piper, leading children and the famous teddy bear "to you". Children are wearing sashes labeled "Good Cheer", "Health", etc.
- No title, 1935 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows Mark Twain toasting
- No title, 1936 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows 10 persons/ideas which are "gone with the wind", including "Mr. Pickwick", "Selassie", "Horace", "Patrick Henry", "W.S. Gilbert", "Liberty", "Erasmus", "King George", and "Old Spain"
- No title, 1938 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows teddy beat sitting on Uncle Sam's lap, saying "What better place to have a Merry Christmas?"; Strewn around Uncle Sam's feet and armchair are headlines about the war in Europe
- No title, 1939 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows teddy bear climbing lamppost at Bancroft place, pointing to Berryman's new home
- No title, 1940 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  General
  This is a Christmas card. Purchased by SCRC 2/14/2011 (accession 2011.012).
- No title, 1941 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows Statue of Liberty, Santa Claus and Nativity Scene
- No title, 1942 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows Uncle Sam and other characters representing world powers looking at a sunrise
- No title, 1943 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
- No title, 1945 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
- No title, 1946 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows scene and verse from Dicken's Pickwick Papers
- No title, undated (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  Christmas card, shows Santa Claus asleep in rocking chair surrounded by laughing children
- no title, 1907 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  shows J.P. Morgan on his knees before Theodore Roosevelt, begging "Save Us, Mr. President, Save Us!"; teddy bear is weeping and "R.R. Magnates" wait in the background
- "The National Motto Gallery", 1907 March 30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  shows unidentified figure and Uncle Sam looking proudly at a framed motto which says "We'll Dig the Ditch or Bust" (probably in reference to Panama Canal); teddy bear looks on with pickax and shovel saying, "You Bet!"
- "The Rival Jefferson Day Dinners", 1907 April 13 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  shows "Miss Democracy" trying to decide which dinner table to sit at: William J. Bryan's, ? Parker's, or ? Hearst's
- No title, 1907 October 07 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  shows footsteps leading to the canebrake, and newspaper/sketch/photograph men and dogs in pursuit; also shows an African American leading a bear cub in chains
- "Portuguese Pickle", 1907 Circa November 25 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  shows King Carlos being tugged by an "Absolutist" and a "Revolutionist"
- "A Suggestion To The House District Committee", 1908 February 06 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  shows persons being ski-lifted to Union Station over a field of snow
- No title, 1908 February 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  shows Uncle Sam assuring elderly bureaucrats that the "Dismissal of Elder Clerks" is "Merely An Annual Spectre"; a teddy bear asks them "Who's Afraid?"
- No title, 1908 February 26 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  shows William Jennings Bryan courting "Democracy" as Wilson and others peek through a window
- No title, 1908 March 17 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  shows "Democracy" being strangled by a serpent "Bryanism" with reptiles "Socialism" and "Populism" close at hand; she cries "Oh, For A St. Patrick!"
- "Taft Luck", 1908 May 07 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  shows William H. Taft riding the "Taft Panama Special"; an avalanche blocks the tracks as he asks "I Wonder If That's An Omen?"
- "Utterly Routed!!!", 1908 September 23 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  shows "General Apathy" being driven back from the White House by Theodore Roosevelt as teddy bear looks on
- "Nebraska's Inspiring Welcome", 1908 October 02 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  shows "Nebraska" pinning a corsage to the breast of William H. Taft; a note at Taft's feet says "Dear Nebraskans- Treat Taft To The Best You Can Hand Out"
- No title, 1908 November 23 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  shows huge "Steel Trust Infant Industry" nursing on "High Protective Tariff" as Uncle Sam and teddy bear look on. Andrew Carnegie opines, "Really, It Can Get Along Without It!"
- No title, 1908 December 02 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  shows Theodore Roosevelt and teddy bear being shielded from storm of "Political Patronage" by an umbrella "Classified Service"; also shows fourth-class postmasters rushing to the umbrella as congressmen throw up their arms
- "The Loving Cup Season", 1909 March 08 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  shows Theodore Roosevelt finding a trophy from the "Late Ananias Club" on his Sagamore Hill doorstep
- No title, 1909 April 20 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  shows jungle animals looking off into the distance, Giraffe saying "It's The Big Smoke, Pals!"; a "News Notes" indicates that this illustration relates to Theodore Roosevelt's arrival at Mombassa on April 21
- No title, 1909 April 28 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  shows decayed "Ananias Club" clubhouse and all its "Annexes" up for sale
- "A Spanish Soliloquy", 1909 October 20 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  shows King Alphonso of Spain on throne, looking at American headlines which ignore the situation in Spain
- "The Czar's Pleasure Trip To Sunny Italy", 1909 October 24 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  shows Czar and army legions marching in Italy
- "Still Hopeful", 1909 October 26 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  shows unidentified sailor figure gazing at "America's Cup" which is locked in a display case
- "Fixing the Blame", 1910 February 10 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  shows well-dressed "Beef Trust" pointing to poor farmer as "The Guilty Cause of High Prices"
- "It May Come To This If The Upward Price Of Hogs Continues", 1910 March 14 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  shows hogs pulling the carriage of a wealthy man
- "An Easter Symphony", 1910 March 27 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  shows politicos walking arm in arm
- "Squash Center Shows Interest In Public Questions", 1910 April 03 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  shows men on the porch of a general store
- "Progressive Kansas", 1911 April 13 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  shows several scenes of a female police officer, i.e.---- looking at hats in a shop window, being frightened of rats, etc.; a "News Note" adds that "The New Woman Mayor Of A Kansas Town Has Appointed A Woman As Chief Of Police"
- "A Spring Caller At The White House", 1910 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  shows William H. Taft holding a bouquet given to him from William R. Hearst, as teddy bear watches
- "Commemorating Geo. V", 1910 May 07 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  shows a throne with a wreath from "America" at its feet
- "More Popular Than The Ancient Piper!", 1911 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  shows unidentified figure carrying a large block of ice on a hot day as children follow him
- "Blasted Hopes", 1911 October 10 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  shows disappointed man looking at seed catalogues of "giant" potatoes, "king" carrots and other vegetables
- No title, 1912 January 01 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  shows child with various tools and packages marked "New Russian Treaty," "Jackson Day Dinner," and others; Father Time waits in a doorway, and the child comments "I Appear To Be 'It'"
- No title, 1912 January 04 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  shows Lafollette (?) trying to use string and a "Big Stick" to trip William H. Taft and teddy bear, who are sledding down the "nomination track"
- "Suggested As A Design To Perpetuate The Unbossed Saratoga Convention", 1912 September 26 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  shows statue of unidentified figure turning his back on kneeling, pleading politicians
- "The Awakening Rip", 1912 October 06 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  shows Rip Van Winkle reading the standings of baseball clubs for the 1912 season; he is amazed that the Washington Senators are in second place
- "A Distraction", 1913 March 08 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  shows William J. Bryan holding off applications for positions to look at Cuba's amnesty bill
- "Immune", 1913 November 23 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  shows a chicken saying to a turkey that a chicken is "...too valuable to kill". A headline announces that the price of eggs "continues to soar"
- "The Captain's Warning", 1915 November 11 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  shows Woodrow Wilson under the "Administration Umbrella" urging a "Democratic Insurgent" to come out of the rain
- No title, 1917 July 05 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  shows John Bull holding headlines and American flags; he comments "My Word! I Never Thought I'd Enjoy This Celebration So Jolly Well"
- "Decoration Day 1918", 1918 May 30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  shows classical style woman placing wreaths on headstones marked "1776" "1812" "1846" "1861" "1898" and "1918"
- "September Morn", 1923 September 01 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  shows "Peace" dropping an olive branch as shells burst in the sky and ocean
- "Easter Egg Rolling 1927", 1927 April 18 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  shows Al Smith, Mc Adoo, Glass, Ritchies, Reed, and Pomerene with egg baskets as Calvin Coolidge sits and looks on
- "Crossing The Stream", 1928 August 03 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  shows Al Smith leading a woman through a stream rather than over the "Dry Plank". The Dry Plank is "Slippery" he says.
- "The Happy Warrior", 1932 February 08 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  shows Al Smith teaching a donkey that Smith is "The Leader Of His Party"
- "The Lady---'Where Are The Guys That Said It Couldn't Be Done?'", 1932 March 05 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  shows woman walking a tightrope holding "Temporary Chairman Barkley" in one hand and "Permanent Chairman Shouse" in the other
- No title, 1932 March 07 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  shows Uncle Sam and teddy bear leading money out of the "hiding place" in an anti-hoarding campaign"
- No title, 1932 March 19 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  shows Al Smith holding up a placard "The Platform At The Coming Convention Should Be Clear and Concise And Tell The People Just What Democracy Is!"; a donkey studying books on democracy by Bryan, Jefferson and others remarks "You Tell Me, Al!"
- No title, 1932 March 31 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  shows old women commending "Newt" on his opinion that "Congress should be kept in session all the time"
- "Frank's New Idea", 1932 April 09 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  shows Franklin D. Roosevelt leading an ancient man who represents "Restore The Purchasing Power To The Farmer"
- No title, 1932 May 03 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  shows farmwoman "Congress" plucking the feathers of "Government Expenditures" chicken
- No title, 1932 September 17 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  shows Franklin D. Roosevelt as a doctor seeing a sick farmer/patient representing the "Middle West". The Middle West asks, "Yes Doc, They All Say I Need Attention But What Is This Remedy Of Yours?"
- "Circus Days Are Here!", 1933 February 16 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  shows "Manager Farley" as a barker, showing boys into a tent of "Numberless Political Performances"
- No title, 1933 March 07 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  shows lumberjacks "House" and "Senate" sawing the log of "U.S. Problems". They tell Franklin D. Roosevelt, "You Tell 'Em, Frank!"
- No title, 1933 November 05 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  shows Herbert Hoover gleefully fishing as headlines of "Farmers Revolt" "Farley Fights Tammany" and others lie across his lap
- "The New Davy Crockett", 1934 January 13 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  shows a racoon "House" sitting on the "Legislative Branch" begging Franklin D. Roosevelt not to shoot
- "Speaking Of Marathoners", 1934 June 08 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  shows FDR, Uncle Sam and teddy bear watching glumly as Finland crosses the finish line of "June 15". Belgium, England, Italy and France all have their backs turned to the line
- No title, 1937 January 27 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  shows Hitler, Stalin, and Italy in the "Dictator's Club" smoking and discussing how FDR can "Get In Step"
- "An Up To Date Admiral Nelson Goes Into Action!", 1938 October 01 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  shows Farley on the "S.S. Democratic Committee" commenting "All Democrats Look Alike To Me!"
- "Speaking Of Sacrifices", 1941 January 13 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  shows taxpayers, Congress, and the military giving up cash, power, and services, respectively, as a laborer asserts "But I'll Never Give Up The Right To Strike!"
- "Capitol Hill Hockey", 1941 January 29 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  shows FDR, the "GOP" (as an elephant) and "Democracy" (as a donkey) on the same team, "...Bound To Score", "Aid To Britain". Shows Wheeler and Nye trying to block the goal with the "Isolation" stick
- "Aid To Britain", 1941 March 07 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  shows Winston Churchill in a wrestling ring being mauled by "Japan" (Hirohito?), Mussolini, and Hitler. Clark, Wheeler, and Nye are behind the ropes, making various accusations against Churchill and Great Britain
- No title, 1941 July 11 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  shows cross-eyed voter being urged in different directions by Franklin D. Roosevelt, Norman Thomas, Al Smith, "N.D.B." "C.C." Garner "Hiram J." Herbert Hoover Ritchie and an unidentified figure
- No title, 1941 July 11 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  shows "D.C." sitting on a curb near the Capitol, listening to rhetoric championing democracy and reviling dictatorship; near him is a headline "Senate Subcommittee Decide Not To Report National Representation Amendment" and he comments "They Do A Lot Of Talking About Democracy, Don't They?"
- No title, 1941 July 27 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  shows taxpayer buried under a pile of ominous headlines as "Congress" prepares to declare a limited emergency. The taxpayer says to Uncle Sam, "I Passed That Stage In 1933"
- No title, 1941 August 17 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  shows Stimson trying to take the new war department building into Arlington. Franklin D. Roosevelt, just coming out of Union Station, catches Stimson in the act. Teddy bear says, "I'm Glad You're Back, Mr. President. They're About To Steal All The Furniture"
- No title, 1941 December 03 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  shows Nomura and Kurusu in a revolving door "War Exit-Peace Exit". Hull tells them they "Have To Decide Where they, Want To Get Out"
- "Hard To Make It Stick", 1942 May 19 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  shows Stalin and Hitler putting up wallpaper marked "Kerch" and "Kharkov". Stalin is tugging on the paper and saying "Now's A Good Time For Somebody To Knock Down The Ladder" that Hitler is standing on
- No title, 1943 January 26 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  shows Wallace painting a portrait of Uncle Sam holding a horn of plenty. Wickard is telling him that the painting "Looks Mighty Nice" but that "It's Going To Be A Hard Winter"
- "A Second Boston Tea Party", 1944 November 02 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  shows FDR and Dewey dumping "Bureaucracy" "Extravagance" "Isolationists" and others overboard
- No title, 1945 May 14 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  shows John Q. Public loading a cannon with a "7th War Loan" amid the spent shells of the 1st through 6th war loans and a destroyed Germany; Uncle Sam urges to keep firing at "Tokyo" with the remark "No Time To Cease Firing Yet"; teddy bear looks at a map of Japan
- No title, 1945 May 24 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  shows Churchill and Atlee beside an old car "Britain's Coalition Movement"; Atlee tells Churchill "It Served Its Purpose. It's Time We Got Started On A New Model"
- No title, 1945 July 29 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  shows Clement Atlee entering in on a meeting between Truman and Stalin; Stalin continues "Now As I Was Saying When So Rudely Interrupted"
- No title, 1945 August 08 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  shows Stimson showing Truman the "Atomic Bomb Report" of "Greatest Achievement Of The Combined Efforts Of Science, Industry, Labor And The Military In All History"; the frightened John Q. Public presents the problem "How To Make People Be Decent To Each Other" and asks Truman to "P-p-p-lease Made Those Scientists Solve This One Real Q-q-q-q-quick!"
- "The Cabinet Meets To Discuss Sending An Ambassador To Mars", 1945 August 09 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  shows Truman and members of the cabinet dressed in Mercury costumes and seated at a round table with "Split Atoms" as the centerpiece
- No title, Circa 1945 (Box 6, Folder 17)